<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Cup Full of Code]]></title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-01T01:18:28.980Z</updated>
  <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Keeler]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[keelerm@tortugas-llc.com]]></email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://zespia.tw/hexo/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[A Look at Vim and Emacs]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2015/03/29/a-look-at-vim-and-emacs/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2015/03/29/a-look-at-vim-and-emacs/</id>
    <published>2015-03-29T10:06:55.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-29T10:25:52.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Thursday, March 26th, 2015 my friend Jacob and I presented to
<a href="http://devict.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">DevICT</a> on what we love about our editors of choice.
Jacob covered vim and I spoke about emacs.</p>
<p>While this talk was billed as a head-to-head competition, neither Jacob nor I
had any intention of &quot;battling it out&quot;.  Instead, we wanted to focus on what we
thought each editor excelled at, and what we in particular liked about
them.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>The talks are available on YouTube, as are all the previous talked by DevICT.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/SaGgc8xnO1U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/3Z4xLZot5h4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>On Thursday, March 26th, 2015 my friend Jacob and I presented to
<a href="http://devict.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">DevICT</a> on what we love about our editors of choice.
Jacob covered vim and I spoke about emacs.</p>
<p>While this talk was billed as a head-to-head competition, neither Jacob nor I
had any intention of &quot;battling it out&quot;.  Instead, we wanted to focus on what we
thought each editor excelled at, and what we in particular liked about
them.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="vim" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/vim/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Invalidate Projectile Cache on Delete]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/</id>
    <published>2014-10-07T01:36:39.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile" target="_blank" rel="external">Projectile</a> is a staple of my emacs
configuration.  In my opinion, it is one of the all time best packages
available, along with <a href="https://github.com/jwiegley/org-mode" target="_blank" rel="external">org-mode</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/magit/magit" target="_blank" rel="external">magit</a>.</p>
<p>One of my most commonly used commands with projectile is helm-projectile.  This
lets me locate any file in my project by pressing <code>C-c p h</code>.  Using the
narrowing abilities of helm, I can quickly filter the list of options to
exactly the one I want.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>Because I work on some projects that are extremely large in size, I have
enabled projectiles caching mechanism.  This tells projectile to maintain a
local cache of all the files within a project for faster searching.  You can
enable this with <code>(setq projectile-enable-caching t)</code></p>
<p>Projectile helps maintain the current state of this cache by adding a hook to
find-file.  Whenever a new file is found or created, projectile will
automatically add that new file to the cache.  This saves me from having to
manually invalidate the cache with <code>C-c p i</code> every time a create a new file.</p>
<p>However, if I delete a file, projectile does not automatically remove it from
the cache.  The next time I search for a similarly named file, the deleted file
will still show up in the helm list of candidates.  While not a deal breaker,
it is certainly a source of annoyance for me.  Since emacs is all about
tweaking your environment to eliminate those little headaches, I knew I had to
fix it.</p>
<p>At first, I thought adding a hook to delete-file would be the easy,
straightforward fix.  I couldn&#39;t find any documentation for a
delete-file-hook.  Having tried to check out the source code, I realized that
while find-file is implemented in lisp, delete-file is actually implemented in
C.</p>
<p>Having been unable to find a hook associated with this function, what was I do
to?</p>
<p>This is where defadvice comes in.  I won&#39;t go into detail about how defadvice
works, but the short version is that defadvice allows you to suggest behavior
to emacs before, after, or around an invocation of a particular function.  You
can read more about
<a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/elisp/Advising-Functions.html" target="_blank" rel="external">defadvice</a>
in the manual.</p>
<p>The below snippet adds advice before the delete-file function is called.  It
checks to see if the file is part of a projectile project; if the file is
cached by projectile, it removes it from the cache.</p>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong> This defadvice function is no longer necessary.  This functionality has
 now been incorporated into projectile.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defadvice</span> delete-file <span class="list">(<span class="title">before</span> purge-from-projectile-cache <span class="list">(<span class="title">filename</span> <span class="keyword">&amp;optional</span> trash)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">and</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">projectile-project-p</span>)</span> projectile-enable-caching)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">let*</span> <span class="list">(<span class="list">(<span class="title">project-root</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">projectile-project-root</span>)</span>)</span></span></span></div><div class="line">             <span class="list">(<span class="title">true-filename</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-truename</span> filename)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">             <span class="list">(<span class="title">relative-filename</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-relative-name</span> true-filename project-root)</span>)</span>)</div><div class="line">        <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">projectile-file-cached-p</span> relative-filename project-root)</span></span></div><div class="line">            <span class="list">(<span class="title">projectile-purge-file-from-cache</span> relative-filename)</span>))))</div><div class="line">  </div><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">ad-activate</span> <span class="quoted">'delete-file</span>)</span></div></pre></figure>

<p>That&#39;s it.  With just a few short lines, projectile will now invalidate the
cache as soon as I delete a file, just as I would like.  Isn&#39;t emacs great?</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile" target="_blank" rel="external">Projectile</a> is a staple of my emacs
configuration.  In my opinion, it is one of the all time best packages
available, along with <a href="https://github.com/jwiegley/org-mode" target="_blank" rel="external">org-mode</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/magit/magit" target="_blank" rel="external">magit</a>.</p>
<p>One of my most commonly used commands with projectile is helm-projectile.  This
lets me locate any file in my project by pressing <code>C-c p h</code>.  Using the
narrowing abilities of helm, I can quickly filter the list of options to
exactly the one I want.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="projectile" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/projectile/"/>
    
      <category term="elisp" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/elisp/"/>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Performing Controlled PHP Refactorings in Emacs]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/09/21/php-refactor-mode/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/09/21/php-refactor-mode/</id>
    <published>2014-09-21T04:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By day, I work as a PHP developer at
<a href="http://researchsquare.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Research Square</a>.  My time is spent developing new
functionality for the RS suite of products.  This may include working in
greenfield code bases or extending our legacy products.  In either case, dozens
of times a day, I find myself performing various code refactorings.<a id="more"></a></p>
<h1 id="The_Problem">The Problem</h1><p>Refactoring code is imperative to maintaining a healthy code base.  Technical
debt can quickly pile up in even a moderately sized code base, let alone across
a system flirting with a million lines of code.  It is the job of any developer
to ensure code is refactored whenever the existing design begins to offer
friction.  It is absolutely critical that these refactorings in no way alter
the behavior of the system.</p>
<p>In Martin Fowler&#39;s book,
<a href="http://martinfowler.com/books/refactoring.html" target="_blank" rel="external">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a>,
he discusses a variety of common refactoring patterns, outlining the necessary
steps to execute these methods safely and efficiently.  While the steps given
are excellent, to perform them manually is not only tedious, but horribly error
prone.</p>
<p>While some IDEs provide automated support for such refactorings, text editors
like vim and emacs do not.  As a long time user of both (with emacs being my
favored editor these days), I needed to look elsewhere to achieve this kind of
support.</p>
<h1 id="The_Solution">The Solution</h1><p>During my search for a decent solution, I came across the
<a href="https://github.com/QafooLabs/php-refactoring-browser" target="_blank" rel="external">php-refactoring-browser</a>
by QafooLabs.  The php-refactoring-browser is a command-line tool, written in
PHP, that can perform a variety of refactoring methods on a particular file.
Following the guidelines from Fowler&#39;s books, each refactoring is a series of
simple steps that ensure the system&#39;s behavior is left unaltered.</p>
<h1 id="A_New_Problem">A New Problem</h1><p>I tried out this tool for a while and absolutely loved the results.  The
php-refactoring-browser performed remarkably well and provided me with a
solution I had desperately been seeking.  But alas, there was a problem.</p>
<p>While I love the command-line, using the php-refactoring-browser
directly was time consuming and frankly, quite annoying.  Each refactoring
method requires a decent number of arguments, including the file and associated
line numbers to operate on.</p>
<p>For example, in order to convert a local variable to an instance variable, the
command would look something like</p>
<figure class="highlight bash"><pre><div class="line">php refactor.phar convert-local-to-instance-variable FileToRefactor.php <span class="number">17</span> <span class="variable">$aLocalVariableName</span></div></pre></figure>    

<p>Further more, the php-refactoring-browser will only generate a patch of the
necessary changes.  It will not modify the files inline.  Not only was I
responsible for providing all of these input parameters, I also had to manually
apply the patch, and then refresh the file in my editor.</p>
<h1 id="A_New_Solution">A New Solution</h1><p>Being an enthusiastic user of emacs, I knew there had to be a better way.  So I
set out to create a minor mode for working with the php-refactoring-browser.
<a href="https://github.com/keelerm84/php-refactor-mode.el" target="_blank" rel="external">php-refactor-mode</a> is the
result.</p>
<p>This minor mode allows you to quickly perform a variety of the refactoring
methods available through the php-refactoring-browser with a few short
keystrokes.  Since emacs already knows the path to the file and any line
numbers, I was relieved from ever having to think about that again.  And as for
things emacs doesn&#39;t know, such as the new method name I might want to use, it
can simply prompt me for it.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the minor mode will automatically apply the resulting patch from
the php-refactoring-browser and re-read the file contents so you can focus on
the work at hand, never breaking your flow to think about the steps for
performing these refactorings.</p>
<p>As a final benefit, each refactoring can be undone as one atomic operation.  So
if you decide you don&#39;t like the results, press <code>C-_</code> and proceed as if it never
happened.</p>
<h2 id="Let&#39;s_See_It_In_Action">Let&#39;s See It In Action</h2><p>Below is a video demoing some of the supported refactoring methods provided by
php-refactor-mode.  If you&#39;re an emacs user who writes PHP, I hope you&#39;ll
consider giving it a try.  The package is available for installation on melpa
and of course the source code is available on github.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/J9lbdtdsPi4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<h1 id="vim_Users">vim Users</h1><p>If you&#39;re a vim user, then you&#39;re in luck.
<a href="https://github.com/vim-php/vim-php-refactoring" target="_blank" rel="external">vim-php-refactoring</a> is a vim
plugin that provides the same type of support.  In fact, it was a great source
of inspiration for my emacs package.  Thanks for paving the way!</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>By day, I work as a PHP developer at
<a href="http://researchsquare.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Research Square</a>.  My time is spent developing new
functionality for the RS suite of products.  This may include working in
greenfield code bases or extending our legacy products.  In either case, dozens
of times a day, I find myself performing various code refactorings.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="php" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/php/"/>
    
      <category term="refactoring" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/refactoring/"/>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="PHP" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/PHP/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Embedding Code Snippets in Org Mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/</id>
    <published>2013-11-22T18:15:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Without a doubt, <a href="http://orgmode.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">Org Mode</a> is one of the most impressive
and versatile features of Emacs.  Great for writing structured documents,
managing lists and planning, and for exporting those documents into a variety
of formats, it&#39;s my go to tool for flexible, efficient editing.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>In the video below, I cover one small aspect of Org Mode; namely, the ability
to embed code snippets within your document.  I&#39;ll cover some of the problems
you will run into when first attempting to embed code, how to overcome them,
and some shortcuts that make the whole process much more streamlined.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/lsYdK0C2RvQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Without a doubt, <a href="http://orgmode.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">Org Mode</a> is one of the most impressive
and versatile features of Emacs.  Great for writing structured documents,
managing lists and planning, and for exporting those documents into a variety
of formats, it&#39;s my go to tool for flexible, efficient editing.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="org-mode" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/org-mode/"/>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Generate Daily Messages With Org Journal]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/17/daily-messages-with-org-journal/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/17/daily-messages-with-org-journal/</id>
    <published>2013-11-17T20:38:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the requirements of my job is to send out a daily message. This message
should summarize what I did the day before, and what I hope to accomplish for
the current day. At first, I would spend my day jumping from task to task, and
then the next morning, I would rack my brain to make sure I included all the
things I worked on.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>It didn&#39;t take long to realize that this was no way to live. I definitely
needed a better solution. So I started looking around.</p>
<h2 id="Org_Journal">Org Journal</h2><p>After hunting around for a bit, I came across Org Journal. It is a fantastic
package for, as the name implies, writing journal entries. And since it&#39;s built
on top of Org Mode, I knew I had to give it a try.</p>
<p>Once installed and configured, I can press, in my case, C-x j, and this will
either start a new journal entry if one doesn&#39;t already exist, or open an
existing one. Each time a new entry is added, org-journal inserts a second
level heading in the document, and stamps it with the time the entry was added.</p>
<p>This was definitely a productivity win for me, and so I settled on it as my
tool of choice.</p>
<h2 id="Scratching_An_Itch">Scratching An Itch</h2><p>Even though org-journal was assisting me in remembering everything I did on the
previous day, I still had to format the entries into a suitable format and send
them off to my boss. Accomplishing this was a multi-step process which I
quickly grew tired of. I had to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Call M-x calendar and navigate to the previous day</li>
<li>Press j to open that day&#39;s journal entry</li>
<li>C-x h to copy the entire entry</li>
<li>C-x b <em>scratch</em> to switch over to my scratch buffer</li>
<li>C-y to paste the journal contents in</li>
<li>Remove any additional notes I had, strip out the top level headers and time stamps, and then add my plan for the current day.</li>
</ol>
<p>What a bunch of nonsense! I certainly wasn&#39;t going to do that 5 days a week for
the rest of my career.</p>
<h2 id="Elisp_to_the_Rescue">Elisp to the Rescue</h2><p>So naturally, I did what any Emacs user would do: I wrote some lisp. Before we
get into the code, I should warn you about something. I&#39;m still pretty new to
lisp. If you&#39;re an old hat at this stuff, I&#39;m sure there are better ways to
accomplish what I&#39;m doing. And I would LOVE to hear about them. Please feel
free to comment!</p>
<p>Disclaimer aside, let&#39;s get into the code.</p>
<h3 id="What_Was_Yesterday">What Was Yesterday</h3><p>The first thing I needed to accomplish was determining the date of the prior
day. Like most people (I hope), I only work 5 days a week. So simply grabbing
yesterday&#39;s date wasn&#39;t going to work. Instead, I need to keep subtracting a
day&#39;s worth of time from the current day, until I reached some time period that
fell between Monday and Friday.</p>
<p>That lead me to:</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> my/org-find-previous-workday <span class="list">()</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">let*</span> <span class="list">(<span class="list">(<span class="title">time</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">time-subtract</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">current-time</span>)</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">seconds-to-time</span> <span class="number">86400</span>)</span>)</span>)</span></span></span></div><div class="line">         <span class="list">(<span class="title">workdays</span> <span class="quoted">'(<span class="string">"Monday"</span> <span class="string">"Tuesday"</span> <span class="string">"Wednesday"</span> <span class="string">"Thursday"</span> <span class="string">"Friday"</span>)</span>)</span>)</div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">while</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">not</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">member</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">format-time-string</span> <span class="string">"%A"</span> time)</span> workdays)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> time <span class="list">(<span class="title">time-subtract</span> time <span class="list">(<span class="title">seconds-to-time</span> <span class="number">86400</span>)</span>)</span>)</span>)</div><div class="line">    time))</div></pre></figure>

<h3 id="Grab_The_Tasks">Grab The Tasks</h3><p>Once I knew the previous working day&#39;s date, I needed to grab the journal
entry&#39;s content. Since I include notes and other references for each entry, and
this email is supposed to be succinct, using the entire journal entry wasn&#39;t
sufficient. Instead, I needed to strip out just the second level headings,
which include short summaries of what I&#39;m working on.</p>
<p>I wrote three functions to handle this, which are included below. The results
of these three functions is to return a list of all the headers in the org file
with a level I specified. If I don&#39;t specify a level, it will return all header
levels.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> my/org-should-include-current <span class="list">(<span class="title">level</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">progn</span></span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">and</span></span></span></div><div class="line">         <span class="list">(<span class="title">outline-on-heading-p</span>)</span></div><div class="line">         <span class="list">(<span class="title">or</span></span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">eq</span> <span class="literal">nil</span> level)</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">eq</span> level <span class="list">(<span class="title">org-outline-level</span>)</span>)</span>))</div><div class="line">        <span class="literal">t</span></div><div class="line">      <span class="literal">nil</span>)))</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> my/org-get-current-header <span class="list">()</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">progn</span></span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> beg <span class="list">(<span class="title">point</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">outline-end-of-heading</span>)</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">buffer-substring-no-properties</span> beg <span class="list">(<span class="title">point</span>)</span>)</span>))</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> my/org-outline-headings-to-list <span class="list">(<span class="title">level</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> headings <span class="quoted">'()</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">show-all</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">goto-char</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">point-min</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-should-include-current</span> level)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">add-to-list</span> <span class="quoted">'headings</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-get-current-header</span>)</span> <span class="literal">t</span>)</span>)</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">while</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">outline-next-heading</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-should-include-current</span> level)</span></span></div><div class="line">        <span class="list">(<span class="title">add-to-list</span> <span class="quoted">'headings</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-get-current-header</span>)</span> <span class="literal">t</span>)</span>))</div><div class="line">  headings)</div></pre></figure>

<h3 id="Generating_The_Message">Generating The Message</h3><p>At this point, I had all the data I needed to quickly generate my scrum
message. All that was left was to hook it together, open a temp buffer with the
formatted results, and then start filling in the current day&#39;s goals.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> my/org-outline-create-scrum-message <span class="list">()</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">interactive</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">let*</span> <span class="list">(<span class="list">(<span class="title">previous</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-find-previous-workday</span>)</span>)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> journal-file <span class="list">(<span class="title">concat</span> org-journal-dir <span class="list">(<span class="title">format-time-string</span> <span class="string">"%Y%m%d"</span> previous)</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-exists-p</span> journal-file)</span></span></div><div class="line">        <span class="list">(<span class="title">progn</span></span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">switch-to-buffer</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">find-file-noselect</span> journal-file)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> headings <span class="list">(<span class="title">my/org-outline-headings-to-list</span> <span class="number">2</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">switch-to-buffer</span> <span class="string">"*daily scrum*"</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">erase-buffer</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">insert</span> <span class="string">"* Yesterday\n"</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">mapcar</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">lambda</span><span class="list">(<span class="title">element</span>)</span></span></span></div><div class="line">                    <span class="list">(<span class="title">insert</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">replace-regexp-in-string</span> <span class="string">"^** ..... "</span> <span class="string">"  - "</span> element)</span> <span class="string">"\n"</span>)</span>) headings)</div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">insert</span> <span class="string">"\n* Today\n  - "</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">org-mode</span>)</span></div><div class="line">          <span class="list">(<span class="title">show-all</span>)</span>))))</div></pre></figure>

<h2 id="Future_Expansion">Future Expansion</h2><p>I have been using this method for the last couple of weeks to much success. It
has saved me a ton of time, and has helped ensure that I account for every task
I worked on during the previous day.</p>
<p>There are a few things I would like to improve. The most obvious next step is
to hook up gnus to my work email and generate this message in an actual email
buffer. Then, once I&#39;m finished typing, I can just send it off directly from
Emacs instead of copy and pasting it into my mail client.</p>
<p>The other thing I need to handle is skipped dates. If I take a vacation day, or
there is a holiday, this code will just fail to generate a message template for
me. It only goes back one day and then calls it quits after that. It wouldn&#39;t
take much to modify it to keep searching until it finds a day with an entry. I
just haven&#39;t gotten around to it yet.</p>
<p>As I mentioned before, I&#39;m sure the code could be improved. I would love to
hear feedback from the community on what I could do better. Lisp is still
pretty new to me, but I&#39;ve been having a blast learning it.</p>
<p>For those interested in seeing the code all in one place, or checking out the
rest of my configuration, you can see it on GitHub.</p>
<p>Thanks, and happy coding!</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>One of the requirements of my job is to send out a daily message. This message
should summarize what I did the day before, and what I hope to accomplish for
the current day. At first, I would spend my day jumping from task to task, and
then the next morning, I would rack my brain to make sure I included all the
things I worked on.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="org-mode" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/org-mode/"/>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="elisp" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/elisp/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Efficient Command Line Navigation]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/07/03/efficient-command-line-navigation/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/07/03/efficient-command-line-navigation/</id>
    <published>2013-07-03T23:36:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I live on the command line. Between <a href="http://www.vim.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">vim</a>,
<a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">tmux</a>, and <a href="http://xmonad.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">xmonad</a>, there
isn&#39;t much I have to use the mouse for these days. Given my love for keyboard
navigation, it only makes sense that I learn as many of the command line
shortcuts available as possible. Here I detail some of the most helpful
navigation tricks, and those I use on a daily basis.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>First a brief word about these shortcut notations. If you see a command listed
as <code>C-a</code>, that is the shorthand representation of pressing Control and a
together. If you see <code>M-b</code>, that is the same as pressing Meta and b
together. Meta is typically Alt on modern systems.</p>
<p>I&#39;m sure everyone knows about <code>TAB</code> completion, but just in case, I feel
compelled to mention it. When working in your shell, you can begin specifying a
file or directory and then use <code>TAB</code> to expand it as far as possible until a
conflict arises. For example, let us assume we have a directory containing the
files matthew.txt, jacob.txt and jacobsen.txt. If I wanted to open matthew.txt
in vim, I can start typing <code>vim m</code> and hit <code>TAB</code> after the <code>m</code>. Since this
character alone is enough to determine uniqueness, my shell will helpfully add
the <code>atthew.txt</code>.</p>
<p>However, if I wanted to open jacobsen.txt, I could type <code>vim j&lt;TAB&gt;</code>, which
would only complete until jacob. After that, the shell cannot possibly know
which file I meant, so it waits for more input. Typing a quick <code>s</code> and <code>TAB</code>;
will finish the job, resulting in <code>vim jacobsen.txt</code>. A lot of shells offer
context aware completion as well. In zsh for example, if I issue <code>git checkout</code>
and hit <code>TAB</code>, I am presented with a list of branches and tags that I can
checkout. Similarly, if I type <code>kill</code> I will get a list of running processes
and their associated PIDs.</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/tab-completion.gif" alt="Tab completion"></p>
<p>There are also a lot of great shortcuts for navigation. For example, let us say
you have typed out the command <code>sp aux | grep &#39;vim&#39; | xargs kill -9</code>. At this
point, you notice you have a typo at the very beginning. You could use your
arrow keys to navigate back to the beginning of the line, delete the two
offending characters, and then use the arrow keys to navigate to the end so you
can continue crafting the command. But this is so time consuming! Instead, we
can use 3 helpful shortcuts -- <code>C-a</code>, <code>C-t</code>, and <code>C-e</code>.</p>
<p><code>C-a</code> will jump your cursor to the start of the line. <code>C-t</code> will transpose the
character under your cursor with the one to the left. In our case, there is no
character to the left, so it simply moves the cursor to the right and then
performs the swap. Now we can jump back to the end of the line with <code>C-e</code>. How
efficient is that?</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/home-transpose-end.gif" alt="Home, Transpose and End"></p>
<p>A quick note about transpose. Vim users beware. This shifting behavior is
different than what you normally experience when issuing <code>xp</code> in command mode,
which swaps the character under the cursor to the right.</p>
<p>What about if the error you made is towards the beginning, but isn&#39;t at the
first character? Once you&#39;ve navigated to the beginning of the command with
<code>C-a</code>, you can move forward a character at a time with <code>C-f</code>, or forward a word
at a time with <code>M-f</code>. In the same spirit, you can move backwards a character
with <code>C-b</code>, or back a word at a time with <code>M-b</code>.</p>
<p>One thing you will soon notice about these commands is that they tend to exist
in pairs. The control options tend to do the least amount of work, whereas meta
will work on a larger scale. So what about our <code>C-t</code> (transpose) option? Does
it have a <code>M-t</code> equivalent? Certainly! This will transpose words.</p>
<p>You might not always want to transpose characters or words. Instead, you may
need to delete some. <code>C-d</code> will delete one character a time, staring with the
character under your cursor. <code>M-d</code> will delete words at a time. Notice though,
that this deletes from the current cursor position to the end of the word. It
does not actually go back to the beginning of the word, and then delete from
there. If you need to delete a word from the current cursor position going
backward, you can use <code>M-backspace</code>.</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/move-delete-transpose.gif" alt="Move, Delete and Transpose"></p>
<p>There are quite a few times I&#39;m crafting a command, and halfway through I
realize I need bail on the command and check something first. But if I <code>C-c</code> to
kill the current command, I&#39;ll have to retype it, and that&#39;s just no
good. Sure, there are ways around this. I could use the mouse to copy the
command and then paste it in later. I could open another tab or tmux window and
check whatever, but that just takes too long. Instead, you can use <code>C-u</code> to cut
the command from your cursor to the beginning of the line, placing that text in
your kill-ring, thereby freeing yourself do whatever you have to do. If you&#39;re
already at the beginning of the command, you can <code>C-k</code> to cut forward from your
cursor position. Once you&#39;re ready to resume that command, you can use <code>C-y</code> to
paste that command back and go on your merry way.</p>
<p>But it gets even better. Let&#39;s say you used the <code>C-u</code> / <code>C-k</code> option a few
times because it is so wicked helpful. But the last thing you cut isn&#39;t what
you want to restore. Use <code>C-y</code> to paste back your last cut, and then use <code>M-y</code>
to cycle through your kill-ring until you find the text you want to restore!</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/kill-ring.gif" alt="Kill Ring"></p>
<p>A lot of times in my workflow, I will edit a file, and then issue a <code>git add
/path/to/file</code> to stage it. I can just type <code>vim /path/to/file</code>, do my edits,
and then issue <code>git add /path/to/file</code>, but that means I have to type the same
file path twice, and I can&#39;t have that, even using <code>TAB</code> completion. The <code>M-.</code>
command saves the day. <code>M-.</code> will insert the last argument from the previous
command at the current cursor location. So now I just type <code>vim /path/to/file</code>,
do my edits, and then git add <code>M-.</code> and the file path is added for
me. Repeating <code>M-.</code> will cycle back through the last parameter for each of the
commands stored in your history.</p>
<p>This post is getting a little lengthy, but there are just a couple more
shortcuts that you simply must know about, and they all deal with your command
history. If you&#39;re anything like me, you tend to issue the same command
multiple times in a day, be it ssh-ing to some host, issuing <code>git status</code> or
what have you. Your shell maintains a history of the commands you have
executed, and you can move back through this history using the arrow keys on
the terminal. But those keys are SO far away from home row!</p>
<p>As you might have surmised, there is a more efficient solution. <code>C-n</code> and <code>C-p</code>
will allow you to navigate through your history going forward and backwards,
respectively.</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/ctrl-n-navigation.gif" alt="Ctrl N Navigation"></p>
<p>If the command you are looking to recall was executed recently, <code>C-n</code> and <code>C-p</code>
are life savers. But if the command is more than a few lines back, they can
quickly become annoying. <code>C-r</code> allows you to issue searches against the command
history. Simply press <code>C-r</code> and then begin typing the command you would like to
recall. As you type more and more characters, the most recent command matching
your search will be displayed. Repeatedly tapping <code>C-r</code> at this point will find
the next most recent command matching the criteria, and so on until all
possible matches have been exhausted. Once you have found the command of
interest, <code>C-j</code> will execute it. If you&#39;d like to select the command, but edit
it first, you can issue any of the navigation commands mentioned above to
select it and start editing. Or, you can type <code>C-g</code> to abort the search, and
your prompt will be restored with whatever text had originally been specified
prior to the search.</p>
<p><img src="../../../../../images/posts/efficient-command-line-navigation/reverse-search.gif" alt="Reverse Search"></p>
<p>I hope you find these commands helpful, and they make working on the command
line a little more enjoyable!  And remember, there are plenty more shortcuts,
so keep learning.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>I live on the command line. Between <a href="http://www.vim.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">vim</a>,
<a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">tmux</a>, and <a href="http://xmonad.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">xmonad</a>, there
isn&#39;t much I have to use the mouse for these days. Given my love for keyboard
navigation, it only makes sense that I learn as many of the command line
shortcuts available as possible. Here I detail some of the most helpful
navigation tricks, and those I use on a daily basis.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="utilities" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/utilities/"/>
    
      <category term="zsh" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/zsh/"/>
    
      <category term="Utilities" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Utilities/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Snippet Expansion with YASnippet]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</id>
    <published>2013-02-26T16:35:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Any editor worth its salt has some provision for text snippet
expansion. TextMate, Vim, and Sublime Text 2 all have this capability and Emacs
is certainly no exception. If you&#39;re not familiar with the concept of snippets,
the basic idea involves defining a keyword, which when followed with some
trigger (keyboard shortcut or menu option), replaces that keyword with some
predefined text. This functionality is a great boost to productivity as it
prevents the developer from having to manually type potentially hundreds or
thousands of lines of relatively boilerplate code.<a id="more"></a></p>
<h2 id="YASnippet">YASnippet</h2><p>Like nearly all things in Emacs, there are a number of available packages that
provide this feature. The one I&#39;ll be discussing today is
<a href="https://github.com/capitaomorte/yasnippet" target="_blank" rel="external">YASnippet (Yet Another Snippet)</a>. The
installation instructions are straightforward and minimal, so I won&#39;t bother
covering them here. Instead, I&#39;ll get right into the meat of the extension.</p>
<h2 id="Plain_Text_Expansion">Plain Text Expansion</h2><p>The most basic functionality any snippet expansion package can offer is
straight text replacement. At first blush, this doesn&#39;t seem terribly helpful,
but let&#39;s consider an example. Suppose I want to include a copy of the GNU
Public License in my project. Copying and pasting such a lengthy license would
quickly grow tiresome for each project you work on. But with the help of
YASnippet, it&#39;s as painless as defining the below snippet and then typing
<code>gpl3</code> and pressing <code>TAB</code> to expand.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"><span class="comment"># name : GPLv3</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># key : gpl3</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># --</span></div><div class="line">                    GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE</div><div class="line">                       Version <span class="number">3</span>, <span class="number">29</span> June <span class="number">2007</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"> Copyright (C) <span class="number">2007</span> Free Software Foundation, Inc. <span class="attribute">http</span>:<span class="regexp">//</span>fsf.org/</div><div class="line"> Everyone <span class="keyword">is</span> permitted to copy <span class="keyword">and</span> distribute verbatim copies</div><div class="line"> <span class="keyword">of</span> <span class="keyword">this</span> license <span class="built_in">document</span>, but changing it <span class="keyword">is</span> <span class="keyword">not</span> allowed.</div><div class="line">  </div><div class="line">                            Preamble</div><div class="line">  </div><div class="line">  The GNU General Public License <span class="keyword">is</span> a free, copyleft license <span class="keyword">for</span></div><div class="line">software <span class="keyword">and</span> other kinds <span class="keyword">of</span> works.</div><div class="line">[...]</div></pre></figure>

<p>You will notice defining this snippet was incredibly easy. The <code>#name : GPLv3</code>
line defines a common name for the snippet. The keyword we will use to trigger
the expansion is defined by <code># key: gpl3</code>. Anything that follows the line <code>#
--</code> will be the replacement text that is inserted when our snippet is
expanded. Phew! That sure saved us a ton of typing. But that&#39;s barely
scratching the surface.</p>
<h2 id="Tab_Stops">Tab Stops</h2><p>While simple text replacement does have its place, it would be more beneficial
if we could add a level of interactivity to the expansion process. This is
where tab stop fields enter the scene. A lot of the boilerplate code a
developer writes is similar, but not quite identical. For example, for loops
follow the same structure, but the initial and terminating conditions,
increment values, and variable names are likely to differ in some regard, so
simple text expansion isn&#39;t quite good enough. So let&#39;s define the following
snippet.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"><span class="comment"># name : for</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># key : for</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># --</span></div><div class="line"><span class="keyword">for</span>(<span class="variable">$1</span>; <span class="variable">$2</span>; <span class="variable">$3</span>) {</div><div class="line">  <span class="variable">$0</span></div><div class="line">}</div></pre></figure>

<p>The <code>$N</code> values will act as tab stops for your cursor when the snippet is
expanded. This means, after expansion, my cursor will stop at <code>$1</code>, allowing me
to specify a value of my choosing. As I successively hit <code>TAB</code>, I will move
through the other tab stops, in numerical order. Upon exiting the expansion, my
cursor will end at <code>$0</code>, which is a special <code>$N</code> type marker. It should be
noted that each of the tab stops can also be defined with default values, using
the syntax <code>${N:default value}</code>. If the defined default value is sufficient,
you can simply tab past it and continue on your way.</p>
<h2 id="Mirrored_Fields">Mirrored Fields</h2><p>While that is pretty awesome, there is a bit of a downside there. In each of
the three stops, if I was using the variable <code>i</code>, I would have to type that in
3 times. <code>i</code> isn&#39;t so bad, but if my variable is
<code>anExtremelyLongAndOverlyVerboseVariable</code>, that is tedious and error
prone. Luckily for us, YASnippet has the answer, and it is mirrored
fields. Mirrored fields allow you to type something in once, and have it
repeated throughout the snippet at other marked placeholders. The initial tab
stop should be defined as <code>${N:enumerate}</code> and each place you want that
information mirrored should use the standard tab notation. Let&#39;s see that in
action!</p>
<p>A common style you&#39;ll see in code is to define an if / while / for block, and
then include a comment at the bottom that reminds the reader of the condition
we&#39;re closing. YASnippet can certainly help us with this. Check out the snippet
below. Type in the condition once, have it included twice. Sweet. Converting
the <code>for</code> snippet is left as an exercise to the reader.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span> (<span class="variable">${1:enumerate}</span>)</div><div class="line">{</div><div class="line"><span class="variable">$0</span></div><div class="line">} // <span class="variable">$1</span></div></pre></figure>

<h2 id="Embedded_Lisp">Embedded Lisp</h2><p>While the above examples have been awesome, the real power of YASnippet has yet
to be revealed. Not only can you include straight text, simple tab stops and
mirrored fields, but you can even include elisp code! The realm of possibility
just got ridiculous.</p>
<p>Let&#39;s look at an example from the C++ <a href="http://qt-project.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">QT</a> world. When
defining QT UI classes, there is some standard code that must be included each
time. Combining the power of mirrored fields with elisp, we can define the
following snippets. You can see them in action on
<a href="http://youtu.be/dlDvDNnsYr4" target="_blank" rel="external">YouTube</a>.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"><span class="comment"># name: QT UI class ... { ... }</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># key: uiclass</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># --</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="comment">#include &lt;$3&gt;</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line">namespace <span class="constant">Ui </span>{</div><div class="line">    class <span class="variable">$1</span>;</div><div class="line">}</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line">class <span class="variable">${</span><span class="number">1</span><span class="symbol">:Name</span>} <span class="symbol">:</span> public <span class="variable">${</span><span class="number">3</span><span class="symbol">:QWidget</span>}</div><div class="line">{</div><div class="line">    <span class="constant">Q_OBJECT</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="symbol">public:</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="variable">$1</span>(<span class="variable">${</span><span class="number">2</span><span class="symbol">:QWidget</span> * parent = <span class="number">0</span>});</div><div class="line">    ~<span class="variable">$1</span>();</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="symbol">private:</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="constant">Ui:</span><span class="symbol">:</span><span class="variable">$1</span> * ui;</div><div class="line">};</div></pre></figure>

<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"><span class="comment"># name: QT UI source</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># key: outsource</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># --</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment">#include "ui_${1:$(downcase yas/text)}.h"</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment">#include "${1:$(downcase yas/text)}.h"</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="variable">${</span><span class="number">1</span><span class="symbol">:Name</span>}<span class="symbol">:</span><span class="symbol">:</span><span class="variable">$1</span>(<span class="constant">QWidget </span>* parent) <span class="symbol">:</span> <span class="variable">${</span><span class="number">2</span><span class="symbol">:QWidget</span>}(parent), ui(new <span class="constant">Ui:</span><span class="symbol">:</span><span class="variable">$1</span>) {</div><div class="line">  ui-&gt;setupUi(this);</div><div class="line">  <span class="variable">$0</span></div><div class="line">}</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="variable">$1</span><span class="symbol">:</span><span class="symbol">:~</span><span class="variable">$1</span>() {</div><div class="line">}</div></pre></figure>

<p>As you can see, the syntax for including elisp is similar to providing default
values for tab stop fields, except all the power of elisp is unleashed!
YASnippet provides a handy placeholder, <code>yas/text</code> which represents the text
that is being mirrored in the field. Using this, you can easily camel case
certain words, upper or lowercase sections of code, and more. But you&#39;re not
limited to just built-in functionality. You can define entirely new functions
of code and reference them just like anything else.</p>
<h2 id="Putting_It_All_Together">Putting It All Together</h2><p>What follows are a few elisp functions I have defined and a snippet that makes
use of them. This snippet will generate the skeleton for a PHP class, including
the namespace at the top. As all of the building blocks have been covered
earlier in this post, I&#39;ll just briefly touch on each portion.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> find-git-repo <span class="list">(<span class="title">dir</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">string=</span> <span class="string">"/"</span> dir)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="literal">nil</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-exists-p</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">expand-file-name</span> <span class="string">".git/"</span> dir)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">        dir</div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">find-git-repo</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">expand-file-name</span> <span class="string">"../"</span> dir)</span>)</span>)))</div></pre></figure>

<p>This function starts looking within a specified directory for the existing of a
.git directory, which would signify we are at the top level of a git
repository. If it doesn&#39;t find it, it keeps looking up the directory structure
until it either succeeds, or reaches the root. If it finds it, we return that
directory. Otherwise, we&#39;ll return nil.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> find-project-root <span class="list">()</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">interactive</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">if</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">ignore-errors</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">eproject-root</span>)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">eproject-root</span>)</span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">or</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">find-git-repo</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">buffer-file-name</span>)</span>)</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-name-directory</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">buffer-file-name</span>)</span>)</span>)</span>))</div></pre></figure>

<p>Using our find-git-repo as a spring board, this function will determine any
project&#39;s root directory. As I use
<a href="https://github.com/jrockway/eproject" target="_blank" rel="external">eproject</a> for a lot of my work, I first
check to see if the <code>eproject-root</code> variable is defined. If it isn&#39;t, I&#39;ll fall
back to looking for a git repo.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> file-path-to-namespace <span class="list">()</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">interactive</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">let</span> <span class="list">(</span></span></div><div class="line">        <span class="list">(<span class="title">root</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">find-project-root</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">        <span class="list">(<span class="title">base</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">file-name-nondirectory</span> buffer-file-name)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">        )</div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">substring</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">replace-regexp-in-string</span> <span class="string">"/"</span> <span class="string">"\\"</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">substring</span> buffer-file-name <span class="list">(<span class="title">length</span> root)</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">*</span> <span class="number">-1</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">length</span> base)</span>)</span>)</span> <span class="literal">t</span> <span class="literal">t</span>)</span> <span class="number">0</span> <span class="number">-1</span>)</span></div><div class="line">    )</div><div class="line">  )</div></pre></figure>

<p>This function will take the current buffer path, find the project root it is
included in, and convert it into a PHP namespace with the portion of the path
containing the project root removed.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line"># name : php-namespaced-<span class="keyword">class</span></div><div class="line"># key : <span class="keyword">class</span></div><div class="line"># --</div><div class="line">&lt;?php</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="javadoc">/**</span></div><div class="line"> * `(file-name-nondirectory (file-name-sans-extension (buffer-file-name)))`</div><div class="line"> *</div><div class="line"> * <span class="javadoctag">@author</span> `(user-full-name)` `(if user-mail-address (concat "&lt;" user-mail-address "&gt;") "")`</div><div class="line"> */</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line">namespace `(file-path-to-namespace)`;</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="javadoc">/**</span></div><div class="line"> * ${1:Description}</div><div class="line"> */</div><div class="line"><span class="class"><span class="keyword">class</span> `<span class="params">(file-name-nondirectory (file-name-sans-extension (buffer-file-name)</span>))`</span></div><div class="line">{</div><div class="line">    $<span class="number">0</span></div><div class="line">}</div></pre></figure>

<p>This final snippet hooks everything up. If I have a project at
<code>/var/www/html/</code>, and I create a file NewUtil.php in say <code>lib/utils/</code>, this
snippet will generate</p>
<figure class="highlight php"><pre><div class="line"><span class="preprocessor">&lt;?php</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="comment">/**</span></div><div class="line"> * NewUtil</div><div class="line"> *</div><div class="line"> *<span class="phpdoc"> @author</span> Matthew M. Keeler &lt;keelerm@tortugas-llc.com&gt;</div><div class="line"> */</div><div class="line">  </div><div class="line"><span class="keyword">namespace</span> <span class="title">lib</span>\<span class="title">utils</span>;</div><div class="line">  </div><div class="line"><span class="comment">/**</span></div><div class="line"> * New Util description goes here</div><div class="line"> */</div><div class="line"><span class="class"><span class="keyword">class</span> <span class="title">NewUtil</span></span></div><div class="line">{</div><div class="line">}</div></pre></figure>

<p>As you can see, the power of YASnippet is incredible. Be sure to check out the
YASnippet repo for more examples of snippets that are included in the default
installation. If any of you are currently using it, I&#39;d love to see some of the
snippets you use. And of course, if you know of ways to improve my examples,
please let me know! Happy coding.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Any editor worth its salt has some provision for text snippet
expansion. TextMate, Vim, and Sublime Text 2 all have this capability and Emacs
is certainly no exception. If you&#39;re not familiar with the concept of snippets,
the basic idea involves defining a keyword, which when followed with some
trigger (keyboard shortcut or menu option), replaces that keyword with some
predefined text. This functionality is a great boost to productivity as it
prevents the developer from having to manually type potentially hundreds or
thousands of lines of relatively boilerplate code.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="org-mode" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/org-mode/"/>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="elisp" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/elisp/"/>
    
      <category term="snippets" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/snippets/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Automation with GNU Screen and SSH]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/08/automation-with-gnu-screen-and-ssh/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/08/automation-with-gnu-screen-and-ssh/</id>
    <published>2013-01-08T18:38:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-03-29T10:10:50.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a developer, I tend to prefer automation whenever possible. Hours of your
life are lost in the minutes spent doing that which could easily be
scripted. The classic rule of thumb I try to follow is &quot;if you have to do it
twice, automate it.&quot;<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>At my job, I have to maintain multiple versions of the product, each of which
are hosted on different virtual machines. When I am ready to start work on a
new feature to an existing version, I have to fire up my code editor, connect
multiple terminals to the system so I can tail various log files, and open a
shell for git. As one can imagine, this is rather time consuming. There is
simply no way I&#39;m doing this by hand every day. To address this, I use a
combination of SSH keys and configs, GNU screen and a small alias.</p>
<p>There are tons of documentation on the web about the use of SSH keys and config
files. If you are unfamiliar with these topics, you can read about SSH keys at
<a href="http://paulkeck.com/ssh/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://paulkeck.com/ssh/</a> and config files at
<a href="http://nerderati.com/2011/03/simplify-your-life-with-an-ssh-config-file/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://nerderati.com/2011/03/simplify-your-life-with-an-ssh-config-file/</a>. Since
the main purpose is to show how my tools fit together, I&#39;ll just state that
every virtual server I connect to has a copy of my SSH key, and that I have a
config file defined with an example snippet shown below:</p>
<figure class="highlight sh"><pre><div class="line">Host <span class="number">19</span></div><div class="line">HostName <span class="number">19</span>.virtualserver</div><div class="line">Port <span class="number">12345</span></div><div class="line">User developer</div></pre></figure>

<p>Each host corresponds to a server hosting a specific version, so instead of
issuing ssh -p12345 developer@19.virtualserver, I can simply type ssh 19. With
the added bonus SSH keys bring to the party, connecting is quick and
simple. But what about all those connections I mentioned earlier?</p>
<p>While it is true I could open multiple terminal tabs, I actually prefer to work
within <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/screen/" target="_blank" rel="external">GNU Screen</a>. Once again, the
details of using screen are outside the scope of this entry, but check out this
post
<a href="http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2004/3/9/16838/14935" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2004/3/9/16838/14935</a>
for some general information.</p>
<p>One thing you don&#39;t hear a lot about is scripting with screen. With the
powerful options provided, you can easily start a screen, launch multiple named
tabs, and execute any command of your choosing. I have a screen config for each
product version I manage. Version 1.9&#39;s config is shown below:</p>
<figure class="highlight sh"><pre><div class="line"><span class="comment"># Start screen in detached mode (-d -m), and give it a session name ('1-9') to avoid</span></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># confusion when communicating with this session later as we add commands</span></div><div class="line">screen <span class="operator">-d</span> -m -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span></div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># Run a command in the current screen window (edit some file for example)</span></div><div class="line">screen -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span> -p <span class="number">0</span> -X title Git</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="comment"># Create a new window, and run a command in that window:</span></div><div class="line">screen -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span> -p <span class="number">0</span> -X screen -t Code emacsclient -nw -c</div><div class="line">screen -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span> -p <span class="number">0</span> -X screen -t Application ssh <span class="number">19</span> <span class="string">'tail -F /var/www/product/logs/error.log'</span></div><div class="line">screen -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span> -p <span class="number">0</span> -X screen -t Apache ssh <span class="number">19</span> <span class="string">'tail -F /var/log/httpd/error.log'</span></div><div class="line">screen -S <span class="number">1</span>-<span class="number">9</span> -p <span class="number">0</span> -X screen -t Remote ssh <span class="number">19</span></div></pre></figure>

<p>Executing this script will create a new screen session with five tabs, giving
me a tab for git, one for my editor of choice, two actively tailing various log
files, and a third connected to the remote system so I can easily navigate and
check out other bits of the system as needed. This script relies heavily on my
aforementioned use of SSH configs and keys. With the keys copied over, I don&#39;t
have to provide a password for the three tabs that connect to the development
box. And if any of the connection details for any of the virtual machines
change, I don&#39;t have to touch this script, and can instead make the
modification in one place.</p>
<p>And finally, just to prevent a few more keystrokes, I also have defined aliases
in my .alias file like the following:</p>
<figure class="highlight sh"><pre><div class="line">alias <span class="string">'19'</span>=<span class="string">'cd ~/Projects/version19; ~/.screen.d/1.9 &amp;&amp; screen -r 1-9'</span></div></pre></figure>

<p>Now, when I&#39;m ready to go to work, I simply open a terminal, type 19, and I&#39;m
automatically thrown into screen, running the applications and viewing the logs
that I almost always need, ready to hit the ground coding with absolute minimal
effort.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>As a developer, I tend to prefer automation whenever possible. Hours of your
life are lost in the minutes spent doing that which could easily be
scripted. The classic rule of thumb I try to follow is &quot;if you have to do it
twice, automate it.&quot;]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="utilities" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/utilities/"/>
    
      <category term="screen" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/screen/"/>
    
      <category term="automation" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/automation/"/>
    
      <category term="Utilities" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Utilities/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Dancing Code Monkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/</id>
    <published>2013-01-06T04:09:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, I started playing around with Emacs.  For roughly six years
prior to that, I was a die-hard Vim fan.  Vim will always hold a special place
in my heart, but I have grown to love Emacs. I&#39;ll undoubtedly cover Emacs in
more detail, but I&#39;ll leave that for other posts.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>One cannot use Emacs for long without dabbling in Elisp, the language upon
which Emacs is built.  Having only briefly touched on Lisp languages in
college, I figured it was high time to start the learning process.</p>
<p>Recently, a friend of mine stumbled upon this cute little code monkey on
someone&#39;s Stackoverflow profile.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line">     __</div><div class="line">w  c(..)o  (</div><div class="line"> <span class="command">\_</span>_(-)   __)</div><div class="line">     /<span class="command">\ </span> (</div><div class="line">    /( )__)</div><div class="line">   m /|</div><div class="line">    | <span class="command">\</span></div><div class="line">    m  m</div></pre></figure>

<p>Quite naturally I thought, &quot;I should make him dance.&quot;  As this seemed
relatively simple, I decided to tackle this with Elisp.</p>
<p>I first created four slightly altered copies of the little guy, and with the
code shown below, had him dancing in no time.  You can make him dance
interactively a set number of times by issuing the standard prefix arguments
prior to invoking the function ( e.g. C-u 100 M-x dance-monkey ) or watch him
shake his groove thing on YouTube.</p>
<figure class="highlight lisp"><pre><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> insert-monkey <span class="list">(<span class="title">num</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">interactive</span> <span class="string">"P"</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">erase-buffer</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">insert-file-contents</span> </span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">concat</span> <span class="string">"/home/keelerm/Projects/emacs/code-monkey/"</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">int-to-string</span> num)</span>)</span>))</div><div class="line"></div><div class="line"><span class="list">(<span class="title">defun</span> dance-monkey <span class="list">(<span class="title">repeat</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">interactive</span> <span class="string">"P"</span>)</span></div><div class="line">  <span class="list">(<span class="title">let</span> <span class="list">(<span class="list">(<span class="title">times</span> <span class="number">0</span>)</span>)</span></span></div><div class="line">    <span class="list">(<span class="title">while</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">&lt;</span> times repeat)</span></span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">insert-monkey</span> <span class="list">(<span class="title">mod</span> times <span class="number">4</span>)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">setq</span> times <span class="list">(<span class="number">1</span>+ times)</span>)</span></div><div class="line">      <span class="list">(<span class="title">sit-for</span> <span class="number">0.2</span>)</span></div><div class="line">      )))</div></pre></figure>

<p>As stated above, I know this is extremely simple, but I suppose everyone has to
start somewhere.  Besides, who doesn&#39;t love a dancing monkey?</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, I started playing around with Emacs.  For roughly six years
prior to that, I was a die-hard Vim fan.  Vim will always hold a special place
in my heart, but I have grown to love Emacs. I&#39;ll undoubtedly cover Emacs in
more detail, but I&#39;ll leave that for other posts.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/emacs/"/>
    
      <category term="elisp" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/elisp/"/>
    
      <category term="Emacs" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Emacs/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Negation and De Morgan's Law]]></title>
    <link href="http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2011/09/01/de-morgans-law/"/>
    <id>http://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2011/09/01/de-morgans-law/</id>
    <published>2011-09-01T04:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2015-02-02T03:31:51.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Undoubtedly, your grade school grammar teacher has scolded you at one point or
another for your inadvertent use of a double negative.  Statements such as I
dont know nothing about physics, while grammatically incorrect, are often
semantically inaccurate as well.  While the previous statement would commonly
be understood to mean the person posses no knowledge of physics, the actual
statement implies the opposite, that the preposition I know nothing about
physics is incorrect.  Certainly your teacher offered sound advice and one
would be wise to heed such instruction.<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>Unfortunately, when programming such double negation is quite common and often
leads to disastrous ends.  For example, who would qualify for the below
condition?</p>
<figure class="highlight php"><pre><div class="line"><span class="preprocessor">&lt;?php</span></div><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span>( !(<span class="variable">$student</span><span class="variable">-&gt;age</span> != <span class="number">18</span> &amp;&amp; !<span class="variable">$student</span><span class="variable">-&gt;enrolled</span>(<span class="string">'Physics'</span>)) ) { ... }</div></pre></figure>

<p>We want someone who is not both not 18 and not enrolled in physics. Simple,
right?</p>
<p>Granted, at the time this snippet was written, it might have been well
understood by the author.  But 6 months later when this line needs altered by a
different developer, precious time is wasted deciphering this twisted logic.</p>
<p>This is where <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Morgan" target="_blank" rel="external">De Morgans Laws</a> come in handy. From Wikipedia:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The negation of a conjunction is the disjunction of the negations.<br>The negation of a disjunction is the conjunction of the negations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Great, so what does that mean? Basically, it means that if you have two
conditions  <code>p</code> and <code>q</code>  and you apply the negation to the statement <code>p and
q</code>, this is logically equivalent to <code>!p or !q</code>. Similarly, if we have the
statement <code>p or q</code> to which we apply the negation operation, this is logically
equivalent to <code>!p and !q</code>.</p>
<p>The easiest way to think about this mentally is that when we apply a negation
across a statement, we prepend each preposition ( either <code>p</code> or <code>q</code> ) with the
<code>not</code> operator, and every time we encounter the logical operators <code>and</code> or
<code>or</code>, we toggle them</p>
<p>Thus, <code>! ( ( p or q ) and ( r or s ) )</code> implies <code>( (!p and !q) or (!r and
!s))</code>.</p>
<p>Using De Morgans law, lets simplify the logic of our initial if condition.</p>
<p>Let us assume the preposition <code>p</code> represents the condition where the students
age is 18 and <code>q</code> represents the condition where the student is enrolled in
physics. Given this, our initial condition can be written in a more compact
form as</p>
<figure class="highlight c"><pre><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span>( !(!p &amp;&amp; !q) ) {</div></pre></figure>

<p>After applying De Morgans Law, we have</p>
<figure class="highlight c"><pre><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span>( !!p || !!q ) {</div></pre></figure>

<p>The negation of the negation of <code>p</code> is <code>p</code>, so the above reduces to</p>
<figure class="highlight c"><pre><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span>( p || q ) {</div></pre></figure>

<p>Substituting <code>p</code> and <code>q</code> for the original conditions, we arrive at the greatly
simplified</p>
<figure class="highlight php"><pre><div class="line"><span class="preprocessor">&lt;?php</span></div><div class="line"><span class="keyword">if</span> ( <span class="variable">$student</span><span class="variable">-&gt;age</span> == <span class="number">18</span> || <span class="variable">$student</span><span class="variable">-&gt;enrolled</span>(<span class="string">'Physics'</span>) ) {</div></pre></figure>

<p>which is much more readily understood.</p>
<p>In order to convince you that the two statements are logically equivalent, a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth_table" target="_blank" rel="external">truth table</a> is provided below. Note
that the second to last column contains the results of the original condition,
and the last column is the reduced condition.</p>
<figure class="highlight text"><pre><div class="line">| p | <span class="string">q | !p |</span> !<span class="string">q | !p &amp;&amp; !q |</span> !(!p ^ !<span class="keyword">q</span>) | p v <span class="string">q |</span></div><div class="line">|---+---+----+----+----------+------------+-------|</div><div class="line">| <span class="number">1</span> | <span class="number">1</span> |  <span class="number">0</span> |  <span class="number">0</span> |        <span class="number">0</span> |          <span class="number">1</span> |     <span class="number">1</span> |</div><div class="line">| <span class="number">1</span> | <span class="number">0</span> |  <span class="number">0</span> |  <span class="number">1</span> |        <span class="number">0</span> |          <span class="number">1</span> |     <span class="number">1</span> |</div><div class="line">| <span class="number">0</span> | <span class="number">1</span> |  <span class="number">1</span> |  <span class="number">0</span> |        <span class="number">0</span> |          <span class="number">1</span> |     <span class="number">1</span> |</div><div class="line">| <span class="number">0</span> | <span class="number">0</span> |  <span class="number">1</span> |  <span class="number">1</span> |        <span class="number">1</span> |          <span class="number">0</span> |     <span class="number">0</span> |</div></pre></figure>

<p>As you can see, De Morgans Law is a powerful tool for managing conditional
complexity in code. I hope this hasnt not helped.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Undoubtedly, your grade school grammar teacher has scolded you at one point or
another for your inadvertent use of a double negative.  Statements such as I
dont know nothing about physics, while grammatically incorrect, are often
semantically inaccurate as well.  While the previous statement would commonly
be understood to mean the person posses no knowledge of physics, the actual
statement implies the opposite, that the preposition I know nothing about
physics is incorrect.  Certainly your teacher offered sound advice and one
would be wise to heed such instruction.]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="logic" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/tags/logic/"/>
    
      <category term="Programming" scheme="http://cupfullofcode.com/categories/Programming/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
