<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Org Mode on Cup Full of Code</title>
    <link>/tags/org-mode/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Org Mode on Cup Full of Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2013 13:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/org-mode/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Embedding Code Snippets in Org Mode</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2013 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, &lt;a href=&#34;http://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;Org Mode&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most impressive
and versatile features of Emacs.  Great for writing structured documents,
managing lists and planning, and for exporting those documents into a variety
of formats, it&amp;rsquo;s my go to tool for flexible, efficient editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate Daily Messages With Org Journal</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the requirements of my job is to send out a daily message. This message
should summarize what I did the day before, and what I hope to accomplish for
the current day. At first, I would spend my day jumping from task to task, and
then the next morning, I would rack my brain to make sure I included all the
things I worked on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet Expansion with YASnippet</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 11:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Any editor worth its salt has some provision for text snippet
expansion. TextMate, Vim, and Sublime Text 2 all have this capability and Emacs
is certainly no exception. If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the concept of snippets,
the basic idea involves defining a keyword, which when followed with some
trigger (keyboard shortcut or menu option), replaces that keyword with some
predefined text. This functionality is a great boost to productivity as it
prevents the developer from having to manually type potentially hundreds or
thousands of lines of relatively boilerplate code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>