<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Cup Full of Code</title>
    <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Cup Full of Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 06:06:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Look at Vim and Emacs</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2015/03/29/a-look-at-vim-and-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 06:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2015/03/29/a-look-at-vim-and-emacs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, March 26th, 2015 my friend Jacob and I presented to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://devict.org/&#34;&gt;DevICT&lt;/a&gt; on what we love about our editors of choice.
Jacob covered vim and I spoke about emacs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this talk was billed as a head-to-head competition, neither Jacob nor I
had any intention of &amp;ldquo;battling it out&amp;rdquo;.  Instead, we wanted to focus on what we
thought each editor excelled at, and what we in particular liked about
them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invalidate Projectile Cache on Delete</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 21:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile&#34;&gt;Projectile&lt;/a&gt; is a staple of my emacs
configuration.  In my opinion, it is one of the all time best packages
available, along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jwiegley/org-mode&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/magit/magit&#34;&gt;magit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most commonly used commands with projectile is helm-projectile.  This
lets me locate any file in my project by pressing &lt;code&gt;C-c p h&lt;/code&gt;.  Using the
narrowing abilities of helm, I can quickly filter the list of options to
exactly the one I want.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Performing Controlled PHP Refactorings in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/09/21/performing-controlled-php-refactorings-in-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2014/09/21/performing-controlled-php-refactorings-in-emacs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By day, I work as a PHP developer at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://researchsquare.com&#34;&gt;Research Square&lt;/a&gt;.  My time is spent developing new
functionality for the RS suite of products.  This may include working in
greenfield code bases or extending our legacy products.  In either case, dozens
of times a day, I find myself performing various code refactorings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embedding Code Snippets in Org Mode</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2013 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/22/embedding-code-snippets-in-org-mode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, &lt;a href=&#34;http://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;Org Mode&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most impressive
and versatile features of Emacs.  Great for writing structured documents,
managing lists and planning, and for exporting those documents into a variety
of formats, it&amp;rsquo;s my go to tool for flexible, efficient editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate Daily Messages With Org Journal</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the requirements of my job is to send out a daily message. This message
should summarize what I did the day before, and what I hope to accomplish for
the current day. At first, I would spend my day jumping from task to task, and
then the next morning, I would rack my brain to make sure I included all the
things I worked on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Command Line Navigation</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/07/03/efficient-command-line-navigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 19:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/07/03/efficient-command-line-navigation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I live on the command line. Between &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vim.org/&#34;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://tmux.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://xmonad.org/&#34;&gt;xmonad&lt;/a&gt;, there
isn&amp;rsquo;t much I have to use the mouse for these days. Given my love for keyboard
navigation, it only makes sense that I learn as many of the command line
shortcuts available as possible. Here I detail some of the most helpful
navigation tricks, and those I use on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet Expansion with YASnippet</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 11:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Any editor worth its salt has some provision for text snippet
expansion. TextMate, Vim, and Sublime Text 2 all have this capability and Emacs
is certainly no exception. If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the concept of snippets,
the basic idea involves defining a keyword, which when followed with some
trigger (keyboard shortcut or menu option), replaces that keyword with some
predefined text. This functionality is a great boost to productivity as it
prevents the developer from having to manually type potentially hundreds or
thousands of lines of relatively boilerplate code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automation with GNU Screen and SSH</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/08/automation-with-gnu-screen-and-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 13:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/08/automation-with-gnu-screen-and-ssh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a developer, I tend to prefer automation whenever possible. Hours of your
life are lost in the minutes spent doing that which could easily be
scripted. The classic rule of thumb I try to follow is &amp;ldquo;if you have to do it
twice, automate it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dancing Code Monkey</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2013 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I started playing around with Emacs.  For roughly six years
prior to that, I was a die-hard Vim fan.  Vim will always hold a special place
in my heart, but I have grown to love Emacs. I&amp;rsquo;ll undoubtedly cover Emacs in
more detail, but I&amp;rsquo;ll leave that for other posts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Negation and De Morgan&#39;s Law</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2011/09/01/negation-and-de-morgans-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/blog/2011/09/01/negation-and-de-morgans-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, your grade school grammar teacher has scolded you at one point or
another for your inadvertent use of a double negative.  Statements such as “I
don’t know nothing about physics”, while grammatically incorrect, are often
semantically inaccurate as well.  While the previous statement would commonly
be understood to mean the person possesses no knowledge of physics, the actual
statement implies the opposite, that the preposition “I know nothing about
physics” is incorrect.  Certainly your teacher offered sound advice and one
would be wise to heed such instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>