<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Portfolio on Cup Full of Code</title>
    <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Portfolio on Cup Full of Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs Configuration</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/emacs-configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/emacs-configuration/</guid>
      <description>Developers love their editors. Typically, they love one to the exclusion of all others. But this is definitely not the case with me. In fact, you might say I have an editor addiction, having played with vim, Sublime Text, Eclipse, Netbeans, and of course emacs.
My emacs configuration includes elisp code to perform auto installation and updating upon start up, as well as customizations to various packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs Packages</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/emacs-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/emacs-packages/</guid>
      <description>Projectile Projectile is a project interaction library for Emacs. Its goal is to provide a nice set of features operating on a project level without introducing external dependencies(when feasible).
I added some defadvice to the delete-file functionality that would remove the file from the cache automatically, preventing the user from having to manually invalidate everything in order to clean up the file list.
buster-mode buster-mode is a minor mode for emacs to speed up development when writing tests with Buster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitList</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/gitlist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/gitlist/</guid>
      <description>gitlist was built to be a modern web interface for multiple git repositories, using some of the latest frameworks, including Silex and Twig, with Twitter bootstrap for the design.
I have contributed a few patches to this project, such as better handling for raw resource viewing and correcting paths to various commit objects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dotfiles</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/dotfiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/dotfiles/</guid>
      <description>What developer&amp;rsquo;s github account would be complete without a dotfiles repo?
My dotfiles repository is structured to work with homeshick, a bash based management system for maintaing your .dotfiles. It includes the configurations for the tools I use most often, such as vim, tmux, zsh and irssi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>powerline</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/powerline/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/powerline/</guid>
      <description>powerline has quickly become a favorite for command line lovers that want to jazz up their environments. My contribution included adding a segment that would show the number of users connected to the active tmux session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bug Genie</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/buggenie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/buggenie/</guid>
      <description>The BugGenie was the first open source project I contributed to. It is an easy to use issue tracking / project management system, written in PHP.
I have contributed various improvements, including fixing invalid links on generated emails, inappropriate handling of various ajax requests, and a variety of CSS based improvements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>timetrap</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/timetrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/timetrap/</guid>
      <description>timetrap is a simple Ruby based command line application to track your time on various projects. This was the first Ruby project I have contributed to, implementing features such as a filter for viewing &amp;ldquo;todays&amp;rdquo; events, as well as a custom invoice generation formatter built with LaTeX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>find.torrent</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/find-torrent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/find-torrent/</guid>
      <description>This API service was developed in collaboration with my friend Jacob Walker. It is a PHP based REST application, written using the BulletPHP framework, and using the HAL specification.
With this service, you can easily search for torrents from a variety of sources and process one for downloading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ft-nodejs</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/ft-nodejs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/ft-nodejs/</guid>
      <description>The find.torrent service is a fantastic project, but on its own, it isn&amp;rsquo;t very useful. There must be an application built to manipulate it&amp;rsquo;s API.
ft-nodejs is a node.js project built to do exactly this. Using node.js, the jade templating engine, and socket.io, it providers a simple, clean interface to search for torrents from a variety of devices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>php-refactor-mode.el</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/php-refactor-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/php-refactor-mode/</guid>
      <description>The Bug Genie - A friendly project management and issue tracking tool.   Built on top of the php-refactoring-browser, php-refactor-mode.el allows a user to quickly perform automated refactorings from within emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>youtube-dl-gui</title>
      <link>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/youtube-dl-gui/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cupfullofcode.com/portfolio/youtube-dl-gui/</guid>
      <description>The wildly popular youtube-dl python script is an excellent tool for downloading and converting YouTube videos. While it is an awesome tool, it isn&amp;rsquo;t the most user friendly tool for some people.
To make using it easier for my wife, I developed a cross-platform C++ QT GUI that drives the command line utility. Files can be downloaded as video only, audio only, or as both, and automatically converted into a variety of formats.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>