<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elisp on Cup Full of Code</title>
    <link>/tags/elisp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Elisp on Cup Full of Code</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 21:36:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/elisp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Invalidate Projectile Cache on Delete</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 21:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/06/invalidate-projectile-cache-on-delete/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile&#34;&gt;Projectile&lt;/a&gt; is a staple of my emacs
configuration.  In my opinion, it is one of the all time best packages
available, along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jwiegley/org-mode&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/magit/magit&#34;&gt;magit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most commonly used commands with projectile is helm-projectile.  This
lets me locate any file in my project by pressing &lt;code&gt;C-c p h&lt;/code&gt;.  Using the
narrowing abilities of helm, I can quickly filter the list of options to
exactly the one I want.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate Daily Messages With Org Journal</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/17/generate-daily-messages-with-org-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the requirements of my job is to send out a daily message. This message
should summarize what I did the day before, and what I hope to accomplish for
the current day. At first, I would spend my day jumping from task to task, and
then the next morning, I would rack my brain to make sure I included all the
things I worked on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet Expansion with YASnippet</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 11:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/02/26/snippet-expansion-with-yasnippet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Any editor worth its salt has some provision for text snippet
expansion. TextMate, Vim, and Sublime Text 2 all have this capability and Emacs
is certainly no exception. If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the concept of snippets,
the basic idea involves defining a keyword, which when followed with some
trigger (keyboard shortcut or menu option), replaces that keyword with some
predefined text. This functionality is a great boost to productivity as it
prevents the developer from having to manually type potentially hundreds or
thousands of lines of relatively boilerplate code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dancing Code Monkey</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2013 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/01/05/dancing-code-monkey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I started playing around with Emacs.  For roughly six years
prior to that, I was a die-hard Vim fan.  Vim will always hold a special place
in my heart, but I have grown to love Emacs. I&amp;rsquo;ll undoubtedly cover Emacs in
more detail, but I&amp;rsquo;ll leave that for other posts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>